Anshuman Biswas

487 Briggs Crt, Mississauga, ON L5W 0C6, Canada | 647-982-9354 | anshuman@biswas.me | https://biswas.me/

About

Anshuman is a Sr. Engineering Manager at IBM. Having worked in Cloud Computing technologies for over a decade, Anshuman relishes the challenges involved with designing distributed systems. He is proficient at solving hard problems and finds it gratifying to design dev-ops driven simple, elegant and efficient solutions for complex systems. In addition to managing resources in a cloud environment, Anshuman enjoys applying economic constraints to maximize performance while managing costs. He likes to automate the menial parts of his developer life by automating anything repetitive.

Experience

SR. ENGINEERING MANAGER | IBM | JUL 2017 - PRESENT | TORONTO, CA

- Leading a team of developers building Orchestration products for Turbonomic
- Developing highly performant code that runs inside a customer data-center and monitors application performance
- · Developing with Java and Kubernetes on a large software codebase that manages cloud and on-prem workloads
- · Built an automated developer workspace to spin up VMs in local datacenter with Terraform and Ansible
- Built an integration test framework by extending the Robot framework to enable component level testing
- Evangelize and continuously improve software development practices
- Anticipate bottlenecks, make tradeoffs, prioritize tasks and meet deliverables while maintaining technical standards
- Drive integrations with third-party systems such as ServiceNow, Terraform Cloud, Ansible Tower and Flexera

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER | TREND MICRO | JUL 2016 - JUL 2017 | OTTAWA, CA

- Backend Server management, performance tuning of Application Server and DB Server
- Build and test dev-ops pipelines for continuous integration and deployment using agile methodology
- Java for primary development. Manage a distributed application deployed on AWS
- Develop based on a Micro-service architecture and deploy using containerized mechanisms
- Ansible, Chef and Jenkins for maintaining a continuous integration and delivery pipeline

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | CARLETON UNIVERSITY | JAN 2012 - JUN 2016 | OTTAWA, CA

- Extensive use of OpenStack and VMWare's vCloud Director for testing resource scaling
- RESTful, SOAP Web Services API Integration with JAVA for OpenStack and AWS (EC2 and S3)
- Use of Python and **Weka** for predicting data based on different machine learning algorithms

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER | RPSMARF | DEC 2014 - JUN 2016 | OTTAWA, CA

- RPSMARF (https://www.rpsmarf.ca/) is a collaborative cloud web application to share analytics tools and data
- Responsible for moving IOT data from onsite to the Cloud to analyze using domain-specific tools
- Service Discovery using SPARQL. Making non-CLI tools available using an integrated remote desktop using Guacamole
- Responsible for deploying and monitoring resources on an OpenStack cluster provided by CANARIE
- · Built an extensive platform with Graphite, Carbon, Statd and Collectd for monitoring infrastructure
- · Frontend development using Angular.JS and backend development using a Python -Django stack

CHIEF TECHNOLOGY OFFICER | NEAREST INC. | JUL 2012 - DEC 2014 | OTTAWA, CA

• Nearest (https://www.nearest.com) is a hyper-local search engine to help local businesses target nearby consumers

- Built a real-time framework for commutation and search with PHP and Web-Sockets. Also Used Meteor.js, Web-Sockets and WebRTC
- Application deployed on a cloud environment with 'proactive' auto-scaling
- Used Amazon Web Services (EC2 + RDS) for production and an Open Stack Cluster for development
- Dev-ops oriented deployment with Vagrant, Puppet and Chef to ensure consistency. Jenkins for integration management
- Managed a team of 8 to meet weekly project deadlines

SYSTEMS ENGINEER | TATA CONSULTANCY SERVICES LTD. (TCS) | SEP 2009 - IAN 2012 | BENGALURU, IN

- Worked with different data warehousing solutions with SAP. Responsible for creating data models and reports
- Migrated locally deployed applications to the Cloud to leverage benefits of Cloud Computing at its infancy (2009)
- Worked in SAP's ABAP to manage DataSources and provide enhanced features to the Business Warehousing solution
- Delivered professional services to external Customers, from the initial detailed Solution Design, through to Implementation and Customer Acceptance customization, including proof of concepts, Stand-Alone and Inter-Operability Testing, Customer training and on-site support

DEVELOPER | GLOBAL TRAVEL SOLUTIONS | AUG 2009 - SEP 2009 | MUMBAI, IN

Worked in the aviation industry to build an integrated travel portal using Google Web Toolkit

INTERN | 2PIRAD | SEP 2007 - APR 2008 | KOLKATA, IN

Built a rudimentary data communication channel using an optical device and a rudimentary OSI layer

Education

PH.D. | ELECTRICAL AND COMPUTER ENGINEERING | 2019 | CARLETON UNIVERSITY

M.SC. | COMPUTER SCIENCE | 2009 | CALCUTTA UNIVERSITY, INDIA

B. SC. | COMPUTER SCIENCE | 2007 | CALCUTTA UNIVERSITY, INDIA

Skills

- · Languages Java Python C PHP JavaScript
- · UX AngularIS
- · Orchestration K8s MicroK8s MiniKube Docker Containerd
- · Databases MySQL Postgres Oracle MongoDB SQL Server Redis
- · Data Streaming Spark Storm Kafka RabbitMQ
- · Frameworks/APIs/Libraries Spring Robot Node.js Meteor.js jQuery Django Laravel
- $\cdot \ \, \textbf{Cloud Providers} \, \text{-} A mazon \text{-} AWS \, IBM \, Cloud \, Azure \, Digital \, Ocean \, Rackspace \, Open Stack \, vCloud \, Cloud \, Azure \, Digital \, Ocean \, Cloud \, Clou$
- · Hypervisors XEN KVM/QEMU ESXi
- · BUILD/CI Maven Gradle Jenkins
- · Servers Apache Nginx Tomcat
- · Search Sphinx ElasticSearch (ELK)
- · Dev-Ops Vagrant Chef Ansible Terraform
- · Version Control GIT SVN